<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>William of Hedon's <title>Tractatus de anima</title></title>
        <author>Michael Stenskjær Christensen</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="1.0.0">
          <title>William of Hedon's Tractatus de anima</title>
          <date when="2018-08-05">August 05, 2018</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</ref></p>
        </availability>
        <date when="2018-08-05">August 05, 2018</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Born digital.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-article-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/article.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the
          LombardPress 1.0.0 guidelines for an article.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2018-08-05" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>File Started for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on"/>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div>
        <head>William of Hedon's <title>Tractatus de anima</title></head>
        <p xml:id="da-3-HedonsDeAnima-muq2zu">
          William of Hedon is the author of <title>Tractatus de anima</title>,
          an independent and original psychological treatise from the last part
          of the 13th century. The identity of the author has not been
          established for certain, but the text is most likely written in an
          English theological context at the beginning of the second half of the
          13th century. This is a an edition of distinction 3, chapter 6 of that
          text, where we find an interesting and highly unique discussion on
          intellectual self-knowledge.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="da-3-HedonsDeAnima-k8errm">
          The text is titled <title>Tractatus de anima</title>, and although it
          has previously been labelled a commentary on Aristotle's <title>De
          anima</title>, it is actually an independent treatise in the tradition
          of Dominicus Gundisalvi, John Blund, William of Auvergne and John of
          la Rochelle. But unlike these authors, William of Hedon most likely
          wrote his text in the second part of the 13th century, at a time when
          the discipline of commenting on Aristotle's <title>De anima</title>
          well established. In this respect it resembles Peter of Spain's
          <title>Scientia de anima</title>, which is either a bit earlier than
          or contemporary with Hedon's treatise. But where Peter of Spain's
          treatise handles the confrontation between the classical tenets of
          orthodox faith with the still stronger presence of Aristotelian
          material by mostly keeping Aristotle out of the discussion, William of
          Hedon engages very actively with the Aristotelian tradition. William's
          approach to Aristotle is pragmatic: when he can use him to establish a
          point, he does so happily, but he feels no obligations of allegiance
          to the Philosopher when he presents his own view on the soul.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="da-3-HedonsDeAnima-d5lt0o">
          Hedon gives an independent presentation of the soul, but the text
          still, as is fairly customary in the genre, partially mirrors the
          structure of Aristotle's text (skipping the historical part of book
          I). It is split into three <title>distinctiones</title>, the first is
          concerned with the science of the soul in general and the definition
          of the soul and its relation to the body, the second book is concerned
          with sense perception, and the third focuses on intellect and the free
          will. The third <title>distinctio</title> a chapter that discusses the
          self-knowledge of the intellect, explicitly addressing the question,
          in the title, how it is possible for the same thing to also be a sign
          of itself.<note>Dist. 3, cap. 6: <quote>Utrum intellectus seipsum
          intelligat et qualiter idem contingat esse signum sui et quid contra
          hoc et ad hoc dici conveniat.</quote></note> Already this title hints
          at the unusual content of the text, and, as we get into the text,
          several interesting irregularities surface. In the preceding section
          (dist. 3, cap. 5, ad fin.) he has argued that in some cases the
          intellect, the intellection, and the object of intellection are the
          same. However, we also presents the philosophical arguments known from
          commentaries on Aristotle's <title>De anima</title> the subject,
          mostly in order to ultimately refute them.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="da-3-HedonsDeAnima-2axp7g">
          The standard position at this time in the faculty of arts is that the
          intellect is only able to know itself once it has been actualized by
          an external species, so William presents five arguments against the
          possibility of immediate intellectual self-knowledge. Some of the
          arguments are commonly known from the commentaries of the arts
          faculty, and thus yield interesting suggestions for how that standard
          view could be countered. But the most interesting arguments are two
          that we do not recognize from the Aristotelian commentaries, and they
          handle the epistemological problem of self-knowledge from a logical
          perspective. In the first of those, the liar paradox is used to
          support the statement that if a part cannot establish knowledge of the
          whole, neither can the intellect establish knowledge of itself. The
          part-whole relationship is compared to the self-reference in the liar
          paradox pointing out that both seem to result in an infinite regress.
          The second semantic argument is based on Aristotle's distinction of
          words as signs of passions of the soul.<note>Aristotle, <title>De
          int.</title> 1.16a3--8</note> argues that, while the intellect is a
          substantial power of the soul, the term `intellect' that is the object
          of self-knowledge is a passion or similitude of the intellect itself,
          and hence an accident of the soul. This means that the subject and
          object of intellection are two distinct things, rendering immediate
          self-knowledge impossible.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="da-3-HedonsDeAnima-lcmxfq">
          William considers the question of self-knowledge relatively
          non-controversial. To him it seems obvious that no one would doubt
          that the intellect knows itself, and that it does so without any
          dependence on external species. But at some point the liar paradox is
          what has really caught his attention. After having resolved the other
          initial arguments, he goes into an extended discussion of that
          problem, which makes up about half the length of the whole chapter.
          The discussion is mostly done with reference to the Aristotelian
          logic, where William shows a deep familiarity with the <term>logica
          nova</term> he draws on <title>Topica</title> <title>Sophistici
          Elenchi</title> as well as <title>Categoriae</title> and <title>De
          interpretatione</title>, but theological authorities also get a place
          in the discussion.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="da-3-HedonsDeAnima-idvhql">
          The use of the liar paradox in the context of psychological
          epistemology is in itself interesting, as William apparently has
          noticed the alignment of the problem of self-reference within the two
          domains. But it is also a testament to the role and weight of the
          logical education within the 13th century universities, when, in the
          composition of a theologically orientated treatise, an author can
          delve into an extended discussion of a logical paradox, that although
          it is well known in the <term>insolubilia</term>-genre, is usually
          confined to collections of <term>sophismata</term>. Finally, it is
          also a unique witness to this strategy of argumentation, as I know of
          no other text, neither earlier nor later, where the liar paradox is
          suggested as an argument against the possibility of immediate
          intellectual self-knowledge.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="da-3-HedonsDeAnima-s16h6k">
          To my knowledge no parts of the text have ever been published. This
          edition of the chapter on self-knowledge will thus in itself present a
          real contribution to our knowledge of a text that is virtually
          unknown. It not only makes available arguments revealing a unique
          blend of logic and epistemology from the last half of the 13th
          century, but will cast some light on the writing process and editorial
          practice of an original, but virtually unknown, author of that period.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
