<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          The edition of William of Hedons <title>Tractatus de anima</title>,
          distinctio 3, chapter 6
        </title>
        <author>Michael Stenskjær Christensen</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="1.0.0">
          <title>
            The edition of William of Hedons <title>Tractatus de anima</title>,
            distinctio 3, chapter 6
          </title>
          <date when="2018-08-05">August 05, 2018</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</ref></p>
        </availability>
        <date when="2018-08-05">August 05, 2018</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Born digital.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-article-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/article.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the
          LombardPress 1.0.0 guidelines for an article.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2018-08-05" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>File Started for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on"/>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div>
        <head>
          The edition of William of Hedons <title>Tractatus de anima</title>,
          distinctio 3, chapter 6
        </head>
        <p xml:id="da3-about-da-3-d3c6-grb9fa">
          There are two witnesses to the text, Cambridge, Gonville & Caius,
          342/538 from the last half of the 13th century (siglum C), and Oxford
          Corpus Christi 107 from the late 13th or early 14th century (siglum
          O), both are English and only contain the text of Hedon. The edition
          is based on digital colour photographs of relatively high quality
          taken by myself.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="da3-about-da-3-d3c6-rfw06q">
          It has been suggested that the Cambridge manuscript is an autograph
          witness by Hedon himself.<note>Montague Rhodes James. <titl>A
          descriptive catalogue of the manuscripts in the library of Gonville
          and Caius College</titl>. 2 vols. Cambridge: Cambridge University
          Press, 1907–1908, p. 386</note> This has not been proven definitively,
          but it is not unlikely. If that is accepted, we can track the
          development of the text and the editorial process of William through
          numerous additions and deletions, often of several columns or whole
          folios. Based on collations with the Oxford witness we can identify at
          least three stages of editing, while I suspect that a fourth stage
          (preceding the three that the collations reveal) can also be
          identified.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="da3-about-da-3-d3c6-ht3qjj">
          I have imposed my own classicising orthography, and my own
          paragraphing and punctuation. Section headings and the structural
          numbers are meta-text added by me. Both scribes make abundant use of
          abbreviations, the expansion of which I generally do not indicate.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
