<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Editorial Principles</title>
        <author>Jeffrey C. Witt</author>
        <author>John T. Slotemaker</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Editorial Principles</title>
          <date when="2018-07-30">July 30, 2018</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</ref></p>
        </availability>
        <date when="2018-07-30">July 30, 2018</date>  
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Born Digital</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-article-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/article.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0 
          guidelines for an article.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2018-07-30" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>File Started for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on"/>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div>
        <head>Editorial Principles</head>
        <p>
          The new digital media affords us the ability to make accessible every level of the 
          editorial process (from manuscript facsimile, to diplomatic transcriptions, 
          to normalized and critical transcriptions) and to provide seamless connections between 
          these data sources at granular levels. 
          For this reason the present edition aims to offer a normalized critical edition that prioritizes
          creating a clean and readable text for the reader.
          As such we have chosen to regularize late medieval orthography.
        </p>
        <p>
          Throughout the edition we have expanded "e" to "ae/oe", regularized late-medieval spelling
          (e.g. changing "sicud" to "sicut") and introduced modern paragraph breaks and modern punctuation 
          in place of late of medieval punctuation. 
        </p>
        <p>
          The choice to privilege a normalized critical text is supported by the fact that, 
          given the possibilities of new media, we are no longer forced to choose between 
          providing a modern normalized text and a diplomatic edition 
          that records the variances and complications of late medieval writing practices. 
          This edition has been prepared in conjunction with the coordinating efforts of 
          the <hi rend="italic">Scholastic Commentaries and Text Archive</hi>, 
          such that every section, paragraph, and quotation can be linked 
          to a diplomatic transcription or multiple diplomatic transcriptions, and further linked 
          to digital facsimiles of the manuscripts themselves. 
          These diplomatic transcriptions are 
          where medieval spelling and punctuation can be recorded 
          at various levels of detail according to the discretion of the editor.
          For this reason, we offer here a normalized edition 
          that can and will function as an access point 
          to subsequent diplomatic transcriptions made available 
          to those with an interest in this kind of textual detail.
        </p>
        <p>
          Given that there is only one extant manuscript of Gracilis's commentary, 
          the critical apparatus aims primarily to 
          record editorial emendations against the text present in the manuscript
          as well as to identify significant scribal corrections.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>