<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Prose Manuscript Description of British Royal 10 A I</title>
        <author>Jeffrey C. Witt</author>
        <author>John T. Slotemaker</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Prose Manuscript Description of British Royal 10 A I</title>
          <date when="2018-07-30">July 30, 2018</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</ref></p>
        </availability>
        <date when="2018-07-30">July 30, 2018</date>  
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Born Digital</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-article-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/article.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0 
          guidelines for an article.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2018-07-30" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>File Started for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on"/>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div>
        <head>Prose Manuscript Description of British Royal 10 A I</head>
        <p>
          Peter Gracilis's commentary on the <title>Sentences</title> is found in a single manuscript witness: London, British Library, Royal ms. 10 A I (siglum L). Codex L contains 238 folios on paper and vellum (for the outer gatherings). It measures 22 cm. x 15 cm. The explicit states that the text was recorded by Johannis Fabri and was completed in 1415. The leaves comprise a single column of text with 38-40 lines in an early fifteenth-century bookhand/Gothic cursive. There are 14 gatherings of 16 leaves (catchwords clearly marked) and a final gathering of 14 leaves. The catchwords are found in the lower-right-hand margin of the corresponding verso leaf and are followed by a note: <hi rend="italic">primus codex</hi> (16v), <hi rend="italic">secundus codex</hi> (32v), <hi rend="italic">codex tertius</hi> (48v), etc.
        <note>
          Here we follow the manuscript description as found in George F. Warner and Julius P. Gilson, <title>Catalogue of Western Manuscripts in the Old Royal and King's Collections</title>, 2 vols. (London, 1921), vol. 1, 300-301.
        </note>
        </p> 
        <p>Provenance: the same scribe completed another commentary on the <title>Sentences</title> (Royal 9 B III), by Giles of Rome, in 1427. Here it is noted that the ms. was completed in Rouen (Explicit ... <hi rend="italic">Scripta per manus fratris Iohannis Fabri conuentus Rothomagensis prefati ordinis, completa die xii. mensis Maii anni dom. m.cccc.xxvii)</hi>. Thus, given that Gracilis lectured at Paris, it seems probable that L originated from Rouen, or, at least, Northern France.</p> 
        <p>Notes of interest: on the fly-leaf preceding the Prologue, in a later hand, is recorded <hi rend="italic">Petrus Gracilis super Sententias</hi>. In the upper margin of f. 1r is written, in two later hands, <hi rend="italic">Assit principio sancta maria meo, etc.</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Petrus Gracilis super Sententias</hi>. Beginning with f. 68v, there is an upper marginal note, in a later hand, indicating the book, distinction/question, etc.; however, it only extends to folio 71r (the rest of the ms. has no textual divisions preserved in the upper margin). L has minor scribal corrections in the margins, often in the same hand. The only decorated initial is found on f. 1r. Subsequent initials are in red and blue and not decorated.</p>
          <p>Finally, the explicit (234v) is written between two names <mentioned>Gualtrinus</mentioned> and <mentioned>Laurecii</mentioned>, which seem joined by some symbolic framework. Is L produced by Gualtrinus Larencii from an original copy produced by Johannis Fabri? It is unclear. Further, it is unclear why Gualtrinus is written and not the more standard Gualterus.</p>
          <p>Contents:
            <list>
              <item>Incipit: <hi rend="italic"><quote>Ascendit Patrus in sueriora domus</quote>...</hi></item>
              <item>Explicit: <hi rend="italic">...per manus fratris Iohannis Fabri dicti ordinis, completumque die xxii. mensis Aprilis, anni m ccccxv. deo gracias. laus tibi sit, Iesu Christe, quoniam liber explicit.</hi></item>
              <item>Principium I: 1r-11v, Incipit:<hi rend="italic"><quote>Ascendit Patrus in superiora domus</quote>...</hi></item>
              <item>Book I, 11v-126r</item>
              <item>Principium II: 126v-134r, Incipit: <hi rend="italic"><quote>Ascendit Patrus in superiora domus</quote>...</hi></item>
              <item>Book II, 134r-192r</item>
              <item>Principium III: 192r-197v, Incipit: <hi rend="italic"><quote>Ascendit Patrus in superiora domus</quote>...</hi></item>
              <item>Book III, 197v-215r</item>
              <item>Principium IV, 215r-219v, Incipit: <hi rend="italic"><quote>Ascendit Patrus in superiora domus</quote>...</hi></item>
              <item>Book IV, 219v-234v</item>
              <item>Tabula quaestionum, 235r-236r</item>
            </list>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>