<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Editorial Principles</title>
        <author>Jeffrey C. Witt</author>
        <author>John T. Slotemaker</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="1.0.0">
          <title>Editorial Principles</title>
          <date when="2023-04-06">April 06, 2023</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/"
              >Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
        <date when="2018-07-30">July 30, 2018</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Born Digital</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-article-1.0.0"
        url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/article.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for an article. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2023-04-06" status="peer-reviewed" n="1.0.0">
          <p>Peer Reviewed</p>
        </change>
        <change when="2018-07-30" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>File Started for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <body>
      <div>
        <head>Editorial Principles</head>
       <!-- <p>
          The new digital media affords us the ability to make accessible every level of the
          editorial process (from manuscript facsimile, to diplomatic transcriptions, to normalized
          and critical transcriptions) and to provide seamless connections between these data
          sources at granular levels. For this reason the present edition aims to offer a normalized
          critical edition that prioritizes creating a clean and readable text for the reader. As
          such we have chosen to regularize late medieval orthography. 
        </p>-->
        <p>
          Throughout the edition we have expanded <hi rend="italic">e</hi> to <hi rend="italic">ae/oe</hi>, regularized late-medieval
          spelling (e.g. changing <hi rend="italic">sicud</hi> to <hi rend="italic">sicut</hi>) and introduced modern paragraph breaks and
          modern punctuation in place of late of medieval punctuation.
        </p>
        <p>
          The choice to privilege a normalized critical text is supported by the fact that, given
          the possibilities of new media, we are no longer forced to choose between providing a
          modern normalized text and a diplomatic edition that records the variances and
          complications of late medieval writing practices. This edition has been prepared in
          conjunction with the coordinating efforts of the <hi rend="italic">Scholastic Commentaries
            and Text Archive</hi> (<ref target="https://scta.info">https://scta.info</ref>), 
          such that every section, paragraph, and quotation can be linked
          to a diplomatic transcription or multiple diplomatic transcriptions, and further linked to
          digital facsimiles of the manuscripts themselves. These diplomatic transcriptions are
          where medieval spelling and punctuation can be recorded at various levels of detail
          according to the discretion of the editor. For this reason, we offer here a normalized
          edition that can and will function as an access point to subsequent diplomatic
          transcriptions made available to those with an interest in this kind of textual detail.
        </p>
        <p>
          Given that there is only one extant manuscript of Gracilis's commentary, the critical
          apparatus aims primarily to record editorial emendations against the text present in the
          manuscript as well as to identify significant scribal corrections. 
          The encoding of the critical apparatus follows the guidelines of the SCTA, 
          which includes a detailed classification schema of variant types. 
          For a detailed description of these variant types see the schema documentation 
          <ref target="https://community.scta.info/pages/lombardpress-schema-critical.html">
            https://community.scta.info/pages/lombardpress-schema-critical.html
          </ref>.
          As much as possible, these variation types have been rendered according 
          to traditional critical apparatus conventions. 
          We hope that these rendered descriptions are clear, but we offer here a quick summary 
          of the most common descriptions found in this rendering. 
        </p>
        <p>
          The abbreviation <hi rend="italic">om.</hi> corresponds to a variation type
          <mentioned>variation-absent</mentioned> and indicates that the lemma in the main 
          text is missing from the manuscript witness. 
          The abbreviation <hi rend="italic">in textu.</hi> corresponds 
          to variation type <mentioned>variation-present</mentioned> and indicates that a word or phrase 
          is present in the manuscript, but the editors chose to exclude this from the main text.
          The abbreviation <hi rend="italic">add.</hi>
          corresponds to <mentioned>correction-addition</mentioned> indicating that the lemma in the main text 
          is present in the manuscript but has been added as kind of correction.
          Finally, <hi rend="italic">add. sed. del</hi>
          corresponds to <mentioned>correction-deletion</mentioned> and indicates that a word was added in the witness
          but subsequently deleted.
        </p>
        <p>
          Nota bene: Peter Gracilis’s commentary on the <title>Sentences</title> borrows heavily from the
          commentary of John of Basel, the first volumes of which were recently published as:
          Iohannis de Basilea OESA. <title>Lectura super quattuor libros Sententiarum. Tomus I, super
          primum librum, principium primum, quaest. 1–3</title>. Ed. Venício Marcolino, cooperantibus Monica
          Brînzei, Carolin Oser-Grote (Würzburg, Augustinus bei echter, 2016); <title>Lectura super
          quattuor libros Sententiarum. Tomus II, super primum librum, quaest. 4–35</title>. Ed. Venício
          Marcolino, cooperantibus Monica Brînzei, Carolin Oser-Grote (Würzburg, Augustinus bei
          echter, 2017); and <title>Lectura super quattuor libros Sententiarum. Tomus III, super secundum
          librum</title>. Ed. Venício Marcolino, cooperantibus Monica Brînzei, Carolin Oser-Grote (Würzburg,
          Augustinus bei echter, 2018). The sources Gracilis references and quotes are often the
          same as those of Basel, with slight modifications. As such, we have benefited greatly
          from the editorial work of Venício Marcolino, Monica Brînzei, and Carolin Oser-Grote. We
          have, of course, checked the references for accuracy.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
